Samuel Hopkins Adams Collection
Samuel Hopkins Adams Collection
1921-1958
Adams, Samuel Hopkins, 1871-1958.
5.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, journalist. Collection is predominantly incoming and outgoing business correspondence with agents and editors concerning Adams' literary works; typescripts of articles, stories, and novels; and photographs. Correspondents includes Brandt & Brandt; Horace B. Liveright of Boni and Liveright; Bennett Cerf and Saxe Commins of Random House; Thomas B. Costain of Doubleday, Doran & Company; Houghton Mifflin Company; Frank G. Slaughter; Merle Thorpe; Irita Van Doran; and Stewart Edward White.
148797
Biographical History
Samuel Hopkins Adams (1871-1958) was an American author. He was born on January 26, 1871, the son of Myron and Hester Rose Hopkins Adams. After receiving his A.B. from Hamilton College in 1891, Samuel Hopkins Adams joined the staff of the New York Sun, moving in 1900 to McClure's magazine, where he became in succession, managing editor, advertising manager, and staff member in the heyday of Lincoln Steffens and Ida M. Tarbell. Eventually, Adams turned to freelance writing and became a highly successful and versatile writer of short stories (many appeared in the New Yorker), biography, and novels dealing with Americana. His most famous books are: Revelry, a story of the Harding administration which was banned in Washington and sold over 100,000 copies, 1926; A. Woollcott: His Life and His World, 1946; Banner by the Wayside, 1947; Plunder, 1948; Sunrise to Sunset, 1950; The Pony Express, 1950; The Santa Fe Trail, 1952; Canal Town, 1953; Grandfather Stories, 1955.
In 1926, Hamilton College awarded Adams an honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters. He died at the age of eighty-seven in Beaufort, South Carolina on November 15, 1958.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Samuel Hopkins Adams Collection consists of manuscripts and correspondence. Correspondence is predominantly incoming and outgoing business correspondence with agents and editors concerning Adams' literary works. Correspondents includes Brandt & Brandt; Horace B. Liveright of Boni and Liveright; Bennett Cerf and Saxe Commins of Random House; Thomas B. Costain of Doubleday, Doran & Company; Houghton Mifflin Company; Frank G. Slaughter; Merle Thorpe; Irita Van Doran; and Stewart Edward White.
Arrangement of the Collection
Writings are alphbetical by type and then by title. Correspondence is chronological.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Literature -- American Fiction; Adams, Samuel Hopkins, 1871-1958.; Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971.; Commins, Saxe.; Costain, Thomas B. (Thomas Bertram), 1885-1965.; Liveright, Horace Brisbin, 1886-1933.; Slaughter, Frank G. (Frank Gill), 1908-2001.; Thorpe, M. H. (Merle Harold), 1879-1955.; Van Doren, Irita Bradford.; White, Stewart Edward, 1873-1946.; Boni & Liveright.; Brandt & Brandt.; Doubleday, Doran & Company.; Houghton Mifflin Company.; Random House (Firm); Authors and publishers.; Authors, American.; Journalists -- United States.; Novelists, American.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.; Journalists.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Photographs gift of Beatrice Champany, 1999.
Inventory
- Manuscripts
  - Short stories
    - Banner by the Wayside, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Blackout, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Chamberlain, Edmund G., article (Box 1)
    - Chance (Box 1)
    - A coat of paint (Box 1)
    - Damage suit industry, outline of series
    - Deadpan, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Emperor Nick of the U.S. Bank (Box 1)
    - Has your car has a soul? (Box 1)
    - Here comes a lady (Box 1)
    - Honor, 1/11/39 (Box 1)
    - Motor vehicle statistics in New Jersey (report), 1923 (Box 1)
    - My venture in anti-witchcraft, 11/15/57 (Box 1)
    - The parson and the factory girl (Box 1)
    - Perfect specimen, 12/1935 (Box 1)
    - Plan for mystery symposium, 10/11/46; script (Box 1)
    - Severus and the oil can, script (Box 1)
    - Short subject (Box 1)
    - Slide, Kellius, Slide (Box 1)
    - Soulcrafter (Box 1)
    - A Third Ward New Year (Box 1)
    - The Timely Death of President Harding (Box 1)
    - Tourists (Box 1)
    - Two Deserters, script (Box 1)
    - Twin towers (Box 1)
    - Westward bound (Box 1)
    - Untitled, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Typescripts
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence with Random House
    - 1942-1943, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1945-1958, 14 folders (Box 3)
    - regarding Harvey Gibbs, 1941-1948; 53 incoming letters, 8 outgoing letters (Box 3)
    - regarding Banner By the Wayside, 1946-1947; 10 incoming letters (Box 3)
    - regarding Sunrise to Sunset, 10 memorandums regarding printing instructions; 8 binding and printing instructions sheets (Box 3)
    - regarding Canal Town, 1943-1944; 15 incoming letters; 11 printing instruction sheets (Box 3)
  - Book correspondence
    - 1925-1939, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - 1940-1944, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - 1949-1957, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Serial correspondence
    - 1921, 1944-1945, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1946-1950, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - 1951-1958, 8 folders (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Master's thesis, "The political and personal factors in the nomination of Warrren G. Harding" / Alder, H. F., for School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University, 1926 (Box 10)
  - Photographs of Samuel Hopkins Adams and Jane Adams, circa 1943 (Oversize 1)